Welcome to our first ever AMR overures
uh discussion. My name is Joel Sinclair
and I'm the pastor of Mosaic Silver
Spring uh in Silver Spring, Maryland and
an executive board member with AMR. Uh
our goal as we talked about in that
first discussion uh that's linked below
is to uh foster a unified and faithful
PCA. And one of the ways that we hope to
do that is uh talking through the work
of the general assembly. Uh what's often
called overtures that is uh requests for
action or amendments that are sent up to
the general assembly often uh are
regularly by prespitaries. Uh today
we're going to take some time and talk
through those overtures with David
Coffin, with Fred Greco, and with Howie
Dano. Uh if you are uh interested in
what these overtures are, there are a
number of them. I should should give you
a heads up, but we've linked below to
where you can find those overtures as
well as where there is a detailed guide
that each of these men have written and
where it it gives their reflections on
these overtures and some uh greater
feedback on them. And so we would just
uh we're linking that below. We'd
encourage you to take a look in this uh
second discussion. What we hope to focus
on is what is it that what information
should higher courts require or request
from our sessions or from uh lower
courts uh particularly when it comes to
things like review. So what kind of
information should be sent up or turned
in? And uh we're going to begin with
overture 8 which came from Nashville
where uh it is an amendment to BCO24
that would uh really direct sessions
when they have candidates for the office
of ruling elder or for deacon that they
would record their differences their
stated differences uh with the
Westminster standards. Um and this is a
practice that happens at the presbyter
level for any teaching elder but this
would extend that to sessions when it
comes to ruling elders and uh to deacons
as well. Uh now in uh their respective
guides uh Howie Dano and David Coffin
both uh suggested that we should answer
this in the negative. Uh Fred Greco
recommended that we should answer in the
affirmative as amended. And so Fred, I'm
going to invite you. Why do you think
this change would be a helpful one uh
for what's required of Sessions? I think
first of all that this concept is
already implicitly required in the book.
But the reason that the BC one of the
reasons the BCO is in a three rings
binder is me and Howie. Um I I've
authored five overtures this year.
Howie, what do you have three or four?
um you know we're we see problems or we
see clarifications and we want to make
it clear in the book and so I think this
will make clear that this is what
sessions should do. Um Howie's guide
makes clear that there's no mechanism
for recording these differences. So
that's what I think the amendment should
be to ask sessions to record it in their
minutes. Now why do I think this is the
case? Well, there's two main arguments.
The first is according to our polity,
ruling and teaching elders are of one
office, two classes within one office.
And so I think if teaching elders are
going to state their differences to the
standards, ruling elders should as well.
I'm less enthusiastic or adamant about
deacons, although I think in the
examination of deacons in the average
PCA church, those examinations
themselves are less thorough and should
be. uh they don't need the same level uh
they don't deacons aren't called to
teach. So you don't need to have the
same level of familiarity with all of uh
the the points of our standards. Uh
secondly, I think this is already a part
of our polity. Uh there's actually the
only case that I'm familiar with that
specifically references a view that may
not be held is Bowen versus um Eastern
Carolina, which was a ruling elder case.
in which a ruling elder took uh ex a
stated difference to infant baptism and
limited atonement and the general
assembly through the SJC said you can't
do that you can't be ordained they
strike as hostile to the system now
that's not the most important
difference with the standards right
those are that's the only ones that have
been adjudicated and so uh I think it
would be helpful for sessions to go
through the exercise of you asking men
if they have a state of difference. Now
again, I don't think this needs to be
some kind of massive inquiry. Uh that
doesn't mean you need to compete
complete a 50-page questionnaire or get,
you know, grilled on every minute point
of doctrine, but there are men by
conscience that take differences with
the standards. And I think for the man's
sake, we should allow him to express
those differences so that he can take
the vow. I I don't really see what the
real problem is for this. I don't see
this as being a significant issue. I I
think it's it's it's already a part of
our policy. Yeah. Thank you, Fred, uh
for giving us your sense of maybe the
slight change in terms of where to
record, but why it's worthwhile to move
forward. Um Howie, David, would you like
to respond with thoughts?
Well, just with the story, I mean, I
I've done this every time I've gone to a
church when I've been considered as an
elder. I give them
I won't tell you how many pages there
are, but I've given them my confessional
differences, but I remember
uh in a large church in the southeast,
I'll just say that. Um I was being
examined
to be I had already I was already
ordained an elder. was being examined to
go on the session. I had given that
document to the three guys that were
going to examine me. I walked in the
room and they looked like they had seen
a ghost. And I said, "What's up?" And
they said, "What's this thing?" I said,
"Those are my differences." What do you
mean those are your differences? I said,
"What do you mean? What do you mean?
What are the Anyway, they said no one in
18 years had ever expressed any
difference with anything in the conf in
the Western Standards."
And I thought, okay, well, that seems
weird, but the longer I've been in the
PCA, the more often I see that in exams.
It's like, no differences, no
differences. Okay, I mean, maybe I'm a
weird dude, but um
uh so I mean, I I have done this every
time when we examine a guy to be an
elder. We ask him, you have you read it?
What do you think? So, um but something
tells me I don't like it. I don't know.
I'll be honest. I don't I just I don't
know.
Yeah. Just for viewers, uh we're not
making a determination on whether it's
weird to have stated differences or not
have stated differences. We're just
thankful for everyone who reflects on
the standards, reads them thoroughly and
then records uh you know, if they find
anything that that that's different.
Yeah. I meant no disparagement. Sorry.
No, no, just I didn't think you did. I
just want to make that crystal clear. Uh
yeah, David, David, do you have any
thoughts on Overture 8?
Well, um my concerns there are not
really relevant in a sense. Um I think
the language that is currently used for
ministers is uh uh
um seriously misguided.
the idea of um
uh striking at the vitals of religion
for example that language historically
that language means uh the ess essential
doctrines of Christianity has nothing to
do with the essential elements of the
standards and I I think it was foolish
for us to ever put that in there. It was
from a very obscure place in the rules
of discipline and I I don't think it
functions well in in uh in the chapter
where it's found and I just assume not
see it in chapter 24 either. So that's
the reason for my objection. So is your
concern strikes at the vitals of
religion or contrary to a fundamental of
the system of doctrine? Those are two
different animals, but it sounds like
you you're saying you don't like the
second animal. I don't like either of
them. Okay. Okay. The the if you say um
fundamentals of the system of doctrine,
I mean Warfield thought every chapter
was fundamental to the system of
doctrine.
That that is not a helpful category. So
it's ahistorical. I don't think it makes
any rational sense. And uh I actually
had a very fine uh uh uh substitute
motion for that in the over bills and
overures committee that year. But uh the
committee decided that if a substitute
motion didn't forward the um view of the
overture itself, it was uh out of order.
Bills and overtures is what overtures
committee used to be called. What year
did it change from bills and overtures
to overtures? Anybody know? When the
same year, same year they got rid of the
yellow pages.
And and and for our our uh most newly
ordained or people to the PC who are
watching, the three- ring binder used to
be the exclusive way in which you would
receive your uh BCO. Now, uh being able
to download it uh from the AC website by
PDF is uh probably used more typical.
Fred, is there a way to distinguish if
someone has uh a blue three three- ring
binder that they're using as opposed to
scrolling on an uh some electronic
device versus like a leatherbound
version of uh you know the three- ring
binder. Does that say something uh about
perspective? I do have a leather bound
version. Yeah, that's right. I do. Um
no, but you know I I think we are
changing this. I I don't think we're
going to change this provision. I have
sympathy with what David's saying, but
as kind of a a practical ex- lawyer,
that ship is sailed uh and landed in
port and they got on a horse and went
down into the barn. That's never going
to get changed. Uh this language we
have, you know, now about strikes at the
vitals or fundamentals. Um and so I just
like to see it brought in alignment. Um
if I we could go back in a time machine
with David, I think I might come up with
a better solution or David could give us
a better solution. I don't see that
happening though and I don't see that
being a fruitful effort at this point.
So while I appreciate, you know, David's
disagreement with that, it seems to me
if that's where we are and what we have,
my my main point would be that we should
treat ruling elders the same way we
treat teaching elders. Let me say we do
New Hope we precisely did that uh and
have have done even before this change
in language. We had them say where they
disagreed and I think that it ought to
be just as carefully done for the
deacons myself uh whether that they are
how's it go in there to be uh competent
in sound doctrine or something that in
the Titus passage I mean and they have
in fact a critical governmental task
Um
that's why I always think it's odd that
uh
but I mean what was their task in Acts
six? It was to adjudicate
uh the fair distribution of the church's
goods to members.
That's a an author authority that
requires careful discernment and
certainly to be a person who's rooted in
sound doctrine. I I I don't think
they're just the guys that mow the lawn
or put up the chairs.
I I want to take maybe a little
difference there. I mean, I agree with
the role that they had. I'm not sure the
guy's view on infant baptism
renders his discernment on how to
distribute the goods
has too much effect on that. I I don't
want to get in that discussion. And we
don't have, you know, deacons that don't
believe in infant baptism, but I'm not
entirely sure.
My theological bar is lower than yours
for deacons, I guess.
Well, it goes to a root uh debate that
we're not taking up as part of our time,
which is um what is uh not only the role
of deacons relative to elders, but then
what authority do they have? And so what
do you need to test or examine uh before
you would ordain such a person to those
roles? Right? And that I think that's a
fair debate. It's it's an open question
uh on the biblical theological
development from Acts 6 through to 1
Timothy 3 and Titus 1, but we we're not
going to take that up today. So, um, uh,
that it's helpful just to to kind of
hear at least from each of you, not only
how you respond, say negative or
affirmative, but what's underneath of
that because sometimes it's different.
And it sounds like it's different from
each of you for different reasons, which
is I hope a challenge to uh those who
are showing up to the the 52nd General
Assembly to kind of think through uh
what is it that's being proposed and and
then how you understand and interpret
that. Um, so next up, uh, we have
overture 34 from Savannah River. And
this overture is not a proposed
amendment to the BCO, but a proposed
amendment to the RAO, which stands for
rules of assembly operation. And what
one thing worth noting is depending on
what happens in the overtures committee
itself, uh, these have a different
voting pathway. So amendments to the BCO
if approved by overtures and then by the
assembly they are sent down to all of
the presbyparies for required two/3s
vote but uh if it's a proposed amendment
to the RAO the rules of assembly
operation then if uh it is taken up or
approved by the overures committee then
that's sent to the assembly itself for
approval. So that particular assembly
would take it up and then it would would
require a twothirds vote of that
particular assembly. If passed it it
goes into effect immediately. Um and so
I just want to highlight this is the
first REO change we're taking up. We've
been talking about BCO changes up to
this point. Overure 34 from Savannah
River is to amend the REO particularly
chapter 16 to require reporting on
session and deaconate membership and
duties. Uh, and so in in looking at uh
the various thoughts or reflections on
34, um, I I'm going to invite Fred uh
just to to respond. In as much as David
and and Howie, you were both negatives
on this, Fred, you were an affirmative
on this. Um, why why did you think this
was a helpful change to the REO, Fred? I
guess the first thing I have to say, and
I put it in my my comments, I'm not sure
the REO is a place to put this. Um, I I
realize that it's easier to amend the
ARO, but it seems to me that this should
probably be in the BCO because I think
what this is getting at is there is a
movement or a tendency in our
denomination
for churches to not ordain men to the
diacinate
because they don't want to have a solely
male diacinet. And so they found a
loophole and that's not ordain anyone
and have a mercy team.
I don't think that's biblical or proper.
I think what our BCO says is if you
don't have deacons, your elders are to
do that work. That's Allah Acts 6. I
think also if you have women to be
involved in the work of mercy and
necessity, you should as a church and
you can have a mercy team and a church
that doesn't have women involved in
diinal ministry. broadly is is in real
trouble. They can't minister I think
properly to the whole of the
congregation.
And so um I think it would be helpful
for us to understand are there churches
like a new church or a church plant that
doesn't have enough men to to do this or
their two deacons moved away or not. Um
I I think there should be a sense in
which every functioning healthy church
should have a session of at least two
men and probably a deaconate of at least
one or two men. Um and if they don't
have a diacinate, they should be able to
give a reason why. So um I don't know
what the language would exactly be.
Again, this might be something I tinker
with in the next week and offer some
amendments cuz I do think the BCCO is
the better place for it to go. Um,
and is that just ask is that is that
because say the BCO is already
addressing certain situations about not
only the role of the deacon in chapter
9, but also as you alluded to kind of
what what would happen in the church if
you didn't have deacons. The these these
kinds of various scenarios are already
um articulated in the BCO itself. So to
jump over to the REO for an amendment,
right? Um is that that's am I
understanding correctly? Yes. And and
the REO is really a reporting
requirement. It doesn't get to the
substance of it. And so I don't know why
you would start with a reporting
requirement without having a BCO
requirement. You know, maybe what you'd
do is you'd make some kind of BCO
amendment and then if you wanted a
reporting requirement, then you could go
to do the REO. But I don't really see
why you start with the reporting
requirement. I think this is more
fundamental to the office of elder, the
office of deacon and and ordination per
se. Yeah.
Any thoughts uh about that, David? I
agree entirely with Fred that it doesn't
belong in the RAO in the first instance.
Um but um
the um
I'll say two things quickly. One, uh I
have written a paper uh that I think
demonstrabably shows that right now the
law of the church is that every
congregation must have the opportunity
for qualified men to become deacons. And
if they're not doing so, they're
violating the constitution of the
church. Uh so I think it's
demonstrabably the case now and thus I
don't think this is needed. Second
though, it strikes me as just a little
Orwellian
that we we have a a a proposition that
on the face of it is just collecting
statistics,
but it underlying is for the purpose of
discovering criminality.
I I just don't like the smell of this
thing.
Yeah. uh the the just to ask my
understanding is there's been also SJC
case law on this or are cases that have
articulated when it's not acceptable to
refuse ordination to a man in a church
who's otherwise qualified or put forward
uh it would violate our standards to
refuse them ordination on some other
principle. I I think we would all agree
on that. That seems to be how um this
has been articulated and then what the
SJC cases rulings have been. Am I
understanding that properly?
Am I missing? I think we have so ruled.
Yeah.
My memory doesn't serve me. I'm There
was a Northwest Georgia case about a guy
that wanted to be a deacon, but I'm not
sure it's precisely what you're saying.
I agree. Yes, I think I was touching on
from California the various views on the
diacinet, right? That this has come up a
few different times uh through
California and possibly through
Philadelphia. We we not that it's going
to be here, but but this question, it's
not a new one to the denomination
through its history on who and how
people can participate um how those
things should be titled or framed and
how to think about it. Um, but it seems
to be accepted that if there's qualified
candidates for ordination in any pathway
that the congregation would have access
or a route to put those qualified people
forward and to vote on them. Um, uh,
Orwellian uh, George Orwell wrote 1984
reference to totalitarian uh, antics uh,
uh, you know, the idea that you would
come up with uh, alternative ways to
sniff out bad things going on. Um, all
right, Howie, go. Well, I I won't use
such a draconian term, but um but it
seems to me if if someone believes, as
Fred was saying, that you have to have
an ordained deacon in it, then then
specifically
write an overture that mandates that and
let the PCA vote on that. this this is
like well okay let's let's collect data
for a future overture or something no
write it now so
one of the things that I wanted to note
is uh because I I think it's rising up
in the conversation there's often quite
a bit of agreement among you three uh
for differing reasons on various
overtures or issues before the court so
in your reflective uh uh writings on all
of the overtures you agreed on overtures
6 7 10 11 13 14, 15, 16, 19, 22, 23, 25,
27, 28, 31, 32, 33, 35, 37, 40, and the
six uh uh change in presbyter boundaries
that are referred to M&A. We agreed on
all that. It makes me tired just hearing
that.
That's more than half. I'm going to have
to go back and revise some of my So, so
that's like 26 out of the 50 one of
those are vacated. there's really like
26 out of the 49 for v varying reasons,
not always the same reasons. You
answered the same in terms of how you
individually would vote on these things.
I just want to highlight that because if
someone's watching this, they're like,
uh, they're they're only picking on the
things that uh maybe there's a bit of a
rub or some disagreement, but even in
that disagreement, there's there's a lot
of unity in terms of how uh you're
approaching these things or the
seriousness or weight that you're giving
them. So, thanks and and I think it's
just worth highlighting for whoever is
listening or watching. Um, okay. There
is a set of three overtures from Cal uh
from Calvary Presbyter which is in South
Carolina. So they these uh three
overtures came up one right after the
other. They were probably submitted as a
package. So they just get ordered. It's
oftent times how these overtures are
numbered. It's just the order in which
they're received by the state at clerk's
office. And so you'll see overures 41,
42, and 43. Uh collecting and reporting
on worship times. Um not collecting on
age and ethnicity. and then an RAO
change uh regarding age and ethnicity.
So these are these are effectively three
things about kind of how we collect data
or are the function of that. Um uh I'm
going to invite uh Howie to kick us off.
Thoughts on uh these three?
You can take them one at a time. You can
talk about them. Yeah. Sure. Sure. Um
the the idea of collecting and reporting
worship times. Two comments real quick.
I think it's very inefficient
because if the clerk's office collected
that and put it on the website,
20% of them would be inaccurate because
they're not updated. So, if I'm in
Milwaukee and I need to find a PCA
church, I it's pretty easy to find and
their times are updated. So, it, you
know, part of me wonders, well, is that
a way to do research on who doesn't have
evening service or something? I don't
know. It just seems odd. Um the thing
about collecting data on age and
ethnicity
um
that one I just couldn't figure out
exactly where the energy was and the
thing that I mean there were some
where's that talked about
uh
the church is just covenant keepers or
covenant breakers I don't know but it
just dawned on him we got nine Korean
Korean presbyaries with 240 plus Korean
churches with 700 plus Korean ministers
that are 14% of the PCA.
That's a pretty ethnic thing. I mean,
would you do we pretend that that
doesn't exist? It just seemed that part
of it seemed odd to me. That's all.
So, my answer, Joel, would be very
boring. It's all about time and effort.
Um,
if the clerk puts on this the form that
comes to us, put your service times,
that takes my secretary 30 seconds to
fill that out.
My congregation has more than 25 nations
represented. And I'm not going to ask
one family that's African-American and
Venezuelan what I should put them down
as and what I should put their kids down
as. Um, you know, maybe that's not true
of every place in the PCA. Houston's the
most diverse city in the world according
to a Rice study. I'm just if that's on
the form, I'm not filling it out. Um,
and I think the reason it came up was
cuz the state clerk announced that they
were going to put that on the form and
they were going to collect it. I don't
have a lot of passion about either of
these cuz all of this is optional. You
know, maybe I could make a gerine
amendment if Howie and David are with me
to do something to get churches to fill
out the report
so we have more than half the churches
fill it out. Maybe we give them a 50
buck break on registration or something.
The the truth of the matter is we don't
really know what the PCA looks like cuz
half the churches don't fill out the
report, right? And I would love to see
effort put there just to be blunt. Yeah.
Just to to be clear for those who are
watching because everyone on this call
or understands um the way in which we
report things like statistics uh right
now there's no mandatory mechanism for
that. What happens is once a year the
state at clerk's office sends out a
request either online or by paper you
can fill it out. Someone at the church
one copy goes to the state at clerk of
every church one copy goes to the pastor
of that church. Uh and then all of that
data is collected that now Howie is
holding up for you uh for the last
yearbook. It gets all collected. But if
you look through that yearbook, you
don't have to look hard. There's
churches we know are particularized by
the record that are listed in a fill-in-
thelank presbyter. And so you can see
them, but then it'll have what year they
last reported. Uh oftentimes it's not
recent. And then they'll have um or
they'll have all blanks all the way
across meaning they haven't reported.
And uh you know so what's being
discussed is well this is all voluntary
which means uh when we think about
church growth as a denomination is is
the denomination growing numerically in
in what ways is it growing um in what
areas is it growing? What prespitary
which of the 87 are we seeing growth or
not? Where are we struggling or is just
difficult work? Um all of those things
are voluntary right now. Uh meaning
every church uh has the ability to fill
it out or not. And and if a church
decides at some point that they want to
adjust their roles and then report it,
that actually can create swings, uh
almost what you would call like uh uh uh
noise in the data because it's like,
"Oh, whoa, what happened there?" Uh it
wasn't uh the the redo of Acts where
3,000 are baptized. It was someone uh
adjusted their roles for the first time
in a number of years, right? Um so
voluntary. You'd like to see incentives
set up to maybe encourage that. Not
necessarily make it mandatory, but at
least uh incentivize it. Okay. Exactly.
On 40. Yeah. Go ahead, David. On 42 and
43, uh I would commend to you the
administrative committee's report. Uh a
lot of times folks don't bother to read
those, but um I think their answer as to
the usefulness of the data and how
they're doing it and why uh in the AC
report was very very helpful.
Thanks so much. Uh I can link that. So
he's talking about the administrative
committee turns in a report for this GA.
So it's in your commissioner's um
handbook for this GA. And if you just
scan down, they'll give response to
that. Um it was uh directed to them uh
for 42 and uh 43 was both overtures as
well as AC because it's the REO change.
Okay. Um anything else on this grouping?
So that covered overures 8, 34, 41, 42,
and 43.
Thanks so much uh for your uh thoughts,
for your comments, for your gracious
interaction. Uh we're grateful for you
joining us today and uh we hope to see
you at General Assembly.